The game Wordle has gone pretty viral in
the last month or two, and never one to
overlook an opportunity for a math
lesson, it occurs to me that this game
makes for a very good central example in
a lesson about information theory, and
in particular a topic known as entropy.
You see, like a lot of people, I got
kind of sucked into the puzzle, and like
a lot of programmers, I also got sucked
into trying to write an algorithm that
would play the game as optimally as it
could. And what I thought I'd do here is
just talk through with you some of my
process in that, and explain some of the
math that went into it, since the whole
algorithm centers on this idea of
entropy.
First things first, in case you haven't
heard of it, what is Wordle? And to kill
two birds with one stone here, while we
go through the rules of the game, let me
also preview where we're going with
this, which is to develop a little
algorithm that will basically play the
game for us. So, I haven't done today's
Wordle, this is February 4th, and we'll
see how the bot does. The goal of Wordle
is to guess a mystery five-letter word,
and you're given six different chances
to guess. For example, my Wordle bot
suggests that I start with the guess
crane. Each time that you make a guess,
you get some information about how close
your guess is to the true answer. Here,
the gray box is telling me there's no C
in the actual answer. The yellow box is
telling me there is an R, but it's not
in that position. The green box is
telling me that the secret word does
have an A, and it's in the third
position. And then there's no N, and
there's no E. So, let me just go in and
tell the Wordle bot that information. We
started with crane, we got gray, yellow,
green, gray, gray.
Don't worry about all the data that it's
showing right now, I'll explain that in
due time, but it's top suggestion for
our second pick is stick. And your guess
does have to be an actual five-letter
word, but as you'll see, it's pretty
liberal with what it will actually let
you guess.
In this case, we try stick.
And all right, things are looking pretty
good. We hit the S and the H, so we know
the first three letters, we know that
there's an R. And so, it's going to be
like S H A something R, or S H A R
something.
And it looks like the Wordle bot knows
that it's down to just two
possibilities, either shard or sharp.
Now, it's kind of a toss-up between them
at this point, so I guess probably just
cuz it's alphabetical it goes with
shard.
Which, hooray, is the actual answer. So,
we got it in three.
If you're wondering if that's any good,
the way I heard one person phrase it is
that with Wordle four is par and three
is birdie. Which I think is a pretty apt
analogy. You have to be consistently on
your game to be getting four, but it's
certainly not crazy. But, when you get
it in three, it just feels great.
So, if you're down for it, what I'd like
to do here is just talk through my
thought process from the beginning for
how I approach the Wordle bot. And like
I said, really it's an excuse for an
information theory lesson. The main goal
is to explain what is information and
what is entropy.
My first thought in approaching this was
to take a look at the relative
frequencies of different letters in the
English language.
So, I thought, okay, is there an opening
guess or an opening pair of guesses that
hits a lot of these most frequent
letters? And one that I was pretty fond
of was doing other followed by nails.
The thought is that if you hit a letter,
you know, you get a green or a yellow.
That always feels good. It feels like
you're getting information. But, in
these cases, even if you don't hit and
you always get grays, that's still
giving you a lot of information since
it's pretty rare to find a word that
doesn't have any of these letters.
But, even still, that doesn't feel super
systematic cuz, for example, it does
nothing to consider the order of the
letters. Why type nails when I could
type snail? Is it better to have that s
at the end? I'm not really sure.
Now, a friend of mine said that he liked
to open with the word wee-wee, which
kind of surprised me cuz it has some
uncommon letters in there like the w and
the y.
But, who knows? Maybe that is a better
opener. Is there some kind of
quantitative score that we can give to
judge the quality of a potential guess?
Now, to set up for the way that we're
going to rank possible guesses, let's go
back and add a little clarity to how
exactly the game is set up. So, there's
a list of words that it will allow you
to enter that are considered valid
guesses that's just about 13,000 words
long. But, when you look at it, there's
a lot of really uncommon things, things
like ahead or ali and arg, the kind of
words that bring about family arguments
in a game of Scrabble. But, the vibe of
the game is that the answer is always
going to be a decently common word. And
in fact, there's another list of around
2,300 words that are the possible
answers. And this is a human-curated
list, I I think specifically by the game
creator's girlfriend, which is kind of
fun. But, what I would like to do, our
challenge for this project, is to see if
we can write a program solving Wordle
that doesn't incorporate previous
knowledge about this list. For one
thing, there's plenty of pretty common
five-letter words that you won't find in
that list. So, it would be better to
write a program that's a little more
resilient and would play Wordle against
anyone, not just what happens to be the
official website. And also, the reason
that we know what this list of possible
answers is is because it's visible in
the source code. But, the way that it's
visible in the source code is in the
specific order in which answers come up
from day to day. So, you could always
just look up what tomorrow's answer will
be.
So, clearly there's some sense in which
using the list is cheating. And what
makes for a more interesting puzzle and
a richer information theory lesson is to
instead use some more universal data,
like relative word frequencies in
general, to capture this intuition of
having a preference for more common
words.
So, of these 13,000 possibilities, how
should we choose the opening guess? For
example, if my friend proposes weary,
how should we analyze its quality?
Well, the reason he said he likes that
unlikely W is that he likes the long
shot nature of just how good it feels if
you do hit that W. For example, if the
first pattern revealed was something
like this, then it turns out there are
only 58 words in this giant lexicon that
match that pattern. So, that's a huge
reduction from 13,000. But, the flip
side of that, of course, is that it's
very uncommon to get a pattern like
this. Specifically, if each word was
equally likely to be the answer, the
probability of hitting this pattern
would be 58 divided by around 13,000.
Of course, they're not equally likely to
be answers. Most of these are very
obscure and even questionable words. But
at least for our first pass at all of
this, let's assume that they're all
equally likely and then refine that a
bit later. The point is the pattern with
a lot of information is by its very
nature unlikely to occur. In fact, what
it means to be informative is that it's
unlikely.
A much more probable pattern to see with
this opening would be something like
this, where of course there's not a W in
it. Maybe there's an E, and maybe
there's no A, there's no R, there's no
Y.
In this case, there were 1,400 possible
matches. So if all were equally likely,
it works out to be a probability of
about 11% that this is the pattern you
would see. So the most likely outcomes
are also the least informative.
To get a more global view here, let me
show you the full distribution of
probabilities across all of the
different patterns that you might see.
So each bar that you're looking at
corresponds to a possible pattern of
colors that could be revealed, of which
there are three to the fifth
possibilities.
And they're organized from left to
right, most common to least common.
So the most common possibility here is
that you get all grays. That happens
about 14% of the time.
And what you're hoping for when you make
a guess is that you end up somewhere out
in this long tail, like over here where
there's only 18 possibilities for what
matches this pattern that evidently look
like this.
Or if we venture a little farther to the
left, you know, maybe we go all the way
over here.
Okay, here's a good puzzle for you. What
are the three words in the English
language that start with a W, end with a
Y, and have an R somewhere in them?
Turns out the answers are, uh, let's
see.
Wordy, wormy, and Riley.
So to judge how good this word is
overall, we want some kind of measure of
the expected amount of information that
you're going to get from this
distribution. If we go through each
pattern and we multiply its probability
of occurring times something that
measures how informative it is, that can
maybe give us an objective score.
Now, your first instinct for what that
something should be might be the number
of matches. You know, you want a lower
average number of matches. But instead,
I'd like to use a more universal
measurement that we often ascribe to
information and one that will be more
flexible once we have a different
probability assigned to each of these
13,000 words for whether or not they're
actually the answer.
The standard unit of information is the
bit, which has a little bit of a funny
formula but is really intuitive if we
just look at examples.
If you have an observation that cuts
your space of possibilities in half, we
say that it has one bit of information.
In our example, the space of
possibilities is all possible words and
it turns out about half of the
five-letter words have an S, a little
less than that but about half.
So, that observation would give you one
bit of information.
If instead a new fact chops down that
space of possibilities by a factor of
four, we say that it has two bits of
information. For example, it turns out
about a quarter of these words have a T.
If the observation cuts that space by a
factor of eight, we say it's three bits
of information and so on and so forth.
Four bits cuts it into a 16th, five bits
cuts it into a 32nd.
So, now is when you might want to take a
moment and pause and ask for yourself,
what is the formula for information, for
the number of bits, in terms of the
probability of an occurrence?
Well, what we're saying here is
basically that when you take 1/2 to the
number of bits, that's the same thing as
the probability, which is the same thing
as saying two to the power of the number
of bits is one over the probability,
which rearranges further to saying the
information is the log base two of one
divided by the probability.
And sometimes you see this with one more
rearrangement still where the
information is the negative log base two
of the probability.
Expressed like this, it can look a
little bit weird to the uninitiated but
it really is just a very intuitive idea
of asking how many times you've cut down
your possibilities in half.
Now, if you're wondering, you know, I
thought we were just playing a fun word
game, why are logarithms entering the
picture? One reason this is a nicer unit
is it's just a lot easier to talk about
very unlikely events. Much easier to say
that an observation has 20 bits of
information than it is to say that the
probability of such and such occurring
is 0.00000095.
But a more substantive reason that this
logarithmic expression turned out to be
a very useful addition to the theory of
probability is the way that information
adds together. For example, if one
observation gives you two bits of
information, cutting your space down by
four, and then a second observation,
like your second guess in Wordle, gives
you another three bits of information,
chopping you down further by another
factor of eight, the two together give
you five bits of information. In the
same way that probability likes to
multiply, information likes to add.
So, as soon as we're in the realm of
something like an expected value, where
we're adding a bunch of numbers up, the
logs make it a lot nicer to deal with.
Let's go back to our distribution for
weary and add another little tracker on
here showing us how much information
there is for each pattern. The main
thing I want you to notice is that the
higher the probability, as we get to
those more likely patterns, the lower
the information, the fewer bits you
gain.
The way we measure the quality of this
guess will be to take the expected value
of this information. Where we go through
each pattern, we say, how probable is
it? And then we multiply that by, how
many bits of information do we get?
And in the example of weary, that turns
out to be 4.9 bits. So, on average, the
information you get from this opening
guess is as good as chopping your space
of possibilities in half about five
times. By contrast, an example of a
guess with a higher expected information
value would be something like slate.
In this case, you'll notice the
distribution looks a lot flatter. In
particular, the most probable occurrence
of all grays only has about a 6% chance
of occurring. So, at minimum, you're
getting evidently 3.9 bits of
information. But that's a minimum. More
typically, you'd get something better
than that. And it turns out, when you
crunch the numbers on this one and you
add up all of the relevant terms, the
average information is about 5.8.
So, in contrast with weary, your space
of possibilities will be about half as
big after this first guess, on average.
There's actually a fun story about the
name for this expected value of
information quantity. You see,
information theory was developed by
Claude Shannon, who was working at Bell
Labs in the 1940s, but he was talking
about some of his yet-to-be-published
ideas with John von Neumann, who was
this intellectual giant of the time,
very prominent in math physics and the
beginnings of what was becoming computer
science. And when he mentioned that he
didn't really have a good name for this
expected value of information quantity,
von Neumann supposedly said, so the
story goes, "Well, you should call it
entropy." And for two reasons. In the
first place, your uncertainty function
has been used in statistical mechanics
under that name, so it already has a
name. And in the second place, and more
important, nobody knows what entropy
really is. So, in a debate, you'll
always have the advantage.
So, if the name seems a little bit
mysterious, and if the story is to be
believed, that's kind of by design.
Also, if you're wondering about its
relation to all of that second law of
thermodynamics stuff from physics, there
definitely is a connection, but in its
origins, Shannon was just dealing with
pure probability theory. And for our
purposes here, when I use the word
entropy, I just want you to think the
expected information value of a
particular guess.
You can think of entropy as measuring
two things simultaneously. The first one
is how flat is the distribution. The
closer a distribution is to uniform, the
higher that entropy will be. In our
case, where there are three to the fifth
total patterns, for a uniform
distribution, observing any one of them
would have information log base two of
three to the fifth, which happens to be
7.92.
So, that is the absolute maximum that
you could possibly have for this
entropy. But, entropy is also kind of a
measure of how many possibilities there
are in the first place. For example, if
you happen to have some word where
there's only 16 possible patterns, and
each one is equally likely. This
entropy, this expected information,
would be four bits. But, if you have
another word where there's 64 possible
patterns that could come up, and they're
all equally likely, then the entropy
would work out to be six bits.
So, if you see some distribution out in
the wild that has an entropy of six
bits, it's sort of like it's saying
there's as much variation and
uncertainty in what's about to happen as
if there were 64 equally likely
outcomes.
For my first pass at the Wordle bot, I
basically had it just do this. It goes
through all of the different possible
guesses that you could have, all 13,000
words. It computes the entropy for each
one, or more specifically, the entropy
of the distribution across all patterns
that you might see for each one, and
then it picks the highest, since that's
the one that's likely to chop down your
space of possibilities as much as
possible.
And even though I've only been talking
about the first guess here, it does the
same thing for the next few guesses. For
example, after you see some pattern on
that first guess, which would restrict
you to a smaller number of possible
words based on what matches with that,
you just play the same game with respect
to that smaller set of words. For a
proposed second guess, you look at the
distribution of all patterns that could
occur from that more restricted set of
words.
You search through all 13,000
possibilities, and you find the one that
maximizes that entropy.
To show you how this works in action,
let me just pull up a little variant of
Wordle that I wrote that shows the
highlights of this analysis in the
margins.
So, after doing all its entropy
calculations on the right here, it's
showing us which ones have the highest
expected information. Turns out the top
answer, at least at the moment, we'll
refine this later, is "tares",
which means,
um,
of course, "avetch", the most common
vetch.
Each time we make a guess here, where
maybe I kind of ignore its
recommendations and go with "slate" cuz
I like slate. We can see how much
expected information it had, but then on
the right of the word here, it's showing
us how much actual information we got
given this particular pattern. So, here
it looks like we were a little unlucky.
We were expected to get 5.8, but we
happened to get something with less than
that. And then on the left side here,
it's showing us all of the different
possible words given where we are now.
The blue bars are telling us how likely
it thinks each word is. So, at the
moment, it's assuming each word is
equally likely to occur, but we'll
refine that in a moment.
And then this uncertainty measurement is
telling us the entropy of this
distribution across the possible words,
which right now, because it's a uniform
distribution, is just a needlessly
complicated way to count the number of
possibilities. For example, if we were
to take 2 to the power of 13.66,
that should be around the 13,000
possibilities. Um a little bit off here,
but only because I'm not showing all the
decimal places. At the moment, that
might feel redundant and like it's
overly complicating things, but you'll
see why it's useful to have both numbers
in a minute. So, here it looks like it's
suggesting the highest entropy for our
second guess is ramen, which again just
really doesn't feel like a word. So,
to take the moral high ground here, I'm
going to go ahead and type in reins.
And again, it looks like we were a
little unlucky. We were expecting 4.3
bits, and we only got 3.39 bits of
information.
So, that takes us down to 55
possibilities.
And here, maybe I'll just actually go
with what it's suggesting, which is
cambu, whatever that means. And okay,
this is actually um a good chance for a
puzzle. It's telling us this pattern
gives us 4.7 bits of information. But
over on the left, before we see that
pattern, there were 5.78 bits of
uncertainty. So, as a quiz for you, what
does that mean about the number of
remaining possibilities?
Well, it means that we're reduced down
to one bit of uncertainty, which is the
same thing as saying that there's two
possible answers. It's a 50/50 choice.
And from here, because you and I know
which words are more common, we know
that the answer should be abyss, but as
it's written right now, the program
doesn't know that. So, it just keeps
going trying to gain as much information
as it can until it's only one
possibility left and then it guesses it.
So, obviously we need a better end game
strategy, but let's say we call this
version one of our Wordle solver and
then we go and run some simulations to
see how it does.
So, the way this is working is it's
playing every possible Wordle game. It's
going through all of those 2315 words
that are the actual Wordle answers. It's
basically using that as a testing set.
And with this naive method of not
considering how common a word is and
just trying to maximize the information
at each step along the way until it gets
down to one and only one choice.
By the end of the simulation, the
average score works out to be about
4.124,
which you know, it's not bad to be
honest. I kind of expected to do worse,
but the people who play Wordle will tell
you that they can usually get it in
four. The real challenge is to get as
many in three as you can. It's a pretty
big jump between the score of four and
the score of three.
The obvious low-hanging fruit here is to
somehow incorporate whether or not a
word is common and how exactly do we do
that?
The way I approached it is to get a list
of the relative frequencies for all of
the words in the English language. And I
just used Mathematica's word frequency
data function, which itself pulls from
the Google Books English Ngram public
data set. And it's kind of fun to look
at. For example, if we sort it from the
most common words to the least common
words, evidently these are the most
common five-letter words in the English
language. Or rather, these is the eighth
most common. First is which, after which
there's there and there. First itself is
not first, but ninth and it makes sense
that these other words could come about
more often. Where those after first are
after, where and those being just a
little bit less common.
Now, in using this data to model how
likely each of these words is to be the
final answer, it shouldn't just be
proportional to the frequency cuz, for
example, which is given a score of 0.002
in this data set, whereas the word braid
is in some sense about a thousand times
less likely. But both of these are
common enough words that they're almost
certainly worth considering. So we want
more of a binary cut-off.
The way I went about it is to imagine
taking this whole sorted list of words
and then arranging it on an x-axis and
then applying the sigmoid function,
which is the standard way to have a
function whose output is basically
binary. It's either zero or it's one,
but there's a smoothing in between for
that region of uncertainty.
So essentially the probability that I'm
assigning to each word for being in the
final list will be the value of the
sigmoid function above wherever it sits
on the x-axis.
Now, obviously this depends on a few
parameters. For example, how wide a
space on the x-axis those words fill
determines how gradually or steeply we
drop off from one to zero.
And where we situate them left to right
determines the cut-off. And to be
honest, the way I did this was kind of
just licking my finger and sticking it
into the wind. I looked through the
sorted list and tried to find a window
where when I looked at it I figured,
"Yeah, about half of these words are
more likely than not to be the final
answer." and used that as the cut-off.
Now, once we have a distribution like
this across the words, it gives us
another situation where entropy becomes
this really useful measurement. For
example, let's say we were playing a
game and we start with my old openers,
which were other and nails, and we end
up with a situation where there's four
possible words that match it. And let's
say we consider them all equally likely.
Let me ask you, what is the entropy of
this distribution?
Well, the information associated with
each one of these possibilities is going
to be the log base two of four, since
each one is one in four, and that's two.
It's two bits of information, four
possibilities. All very well and good.
But what if I told you that actually
there's more than four matches? In
reality, when we look through the full
word list, there are 16 words that match
it. But suppose our model puts a really
low probability on those other 12 words
of actually being the final answer.
Something like one in a thousand cuz
they're really obscure.
Now, let me ask you, what is the entropy
of this distribution?
If entropy was purely measuring the
number of matches here, then you might
expect it to be something like the log
base two of 16, which would be four, two
more bits of uncertainty than we had
before. But of course, the actual
uncertainty is not really that different
from what we had before cuz just because
there's these 12 really obscure words,
doesn't mean that it would be all that
more surprising to learn that the final
answer is charm, for example.
So, when you actually do the calculation
here and you add up the probability of
each occurrence times the corresponding
information, what you get is 2.11 bits.
Which is saying, it's basically two
bits. It's basically those four
possibilities, but there's a little more
uncertainty because of all of those
highly unlikely events. Though, if you
did learn them, you'd get a ton of
information from it.
So, zooming out, this is part of what
makes Wordle such a nice example for an
information theory lesson. We have these
two distinct-feeling applications for
entropy. The first one telling us what's
the expected information we'll get from
a given guess. And the second one
saying, can we measure the remaining
uncertainty among all of the words that
we have possible?
And I should emphasize in that first
case where we're looking at the expected
information of a guess, once we have an
unequal weighting to the words, that
affects the entropy calculation. For
example, let me pull up that same case
we were looking at earlier of the
distribution associated with weary, but
this time using a non-uniform
distribution across all possible words.
So, let me see if I can find a part here
that illustrates it pretty well.
Uh okay, here this is pretty good. Here
we have two adjacent patterns that are
about equally likely, but one of them
we're told has 32 possible words that
match it. And if we check what they are,
these are those 32, which are all just
very unlikely words. As you scan your
eyes over them, you know, it's hard to
find any that feel like plausible
answers. Maybe yells? But if we look at
the neighboring pattern in the
distribution, which is considered just
about as likely, we're told that it only
has eight possible matches. So, a
quarter as many matches, but it's about
as likely. And when we pull up those
matches, we can see why. Some of these
are actual plausible answers, like ring
or wrath or wraps.
To illustrate how we incorporate all
that, let me pull up version two of the
Wordle bot here, and there are two or
three main differences from the first
one that we saw. First off, like I just
said, the way that we're computing these
entropies, these expected values of
information, is now using the more
refined distributions across the
patterns that incorporates the
probability that a given word would
actually be the answer.
Uh as it happens, tears is still number
one, though the ones following are a bit
different. Second, when it ranks its top
picks, it's now going to keep a model of
the probability that each word is the
actual answer, and it'll incorporate
that into its decision, which is easier
to see once we have a few guesses on the
table.
Again, ignoring its recommendation
because we can't let machines rule our
lives,
and I suppose I should mention another
thing different here is over on the
left, that uncertainty value, that
number of bits, is no longer just
redundant with the number of possible
matches. Now, if we pull it up and you
know, we calculate, say, 2 to the 8.02,
which should be a little above 256, I
guess uh 259, what it's saying is even
though there are 526 total words that
actually match this pattern, the amount
of uncertainty it has is more akin to
what it would be if there were 259
equally likely outcomes.
You can think of it like this. It knows
borks is not the answer, same with yorts
and zorl and zoris. So, it's a little
less uncertain than it was in the
previous case. This number of bits will
be smaller.
And if I keep playing the game, I'm
refining this down with a couple guesses
that are apropos of what I would like to
explain here.
By the fourth guess, if you look over at
its top picks, you can see it's no
longer just maximizing the entropy.
So, at this point, there's technically
seven possibilities, but the only ones
with a meaningful chance are dorms and
words. And you can see it ranks choosing
both of those above all of these other
values that strictly speaking would give
more information.
The very first time I did this, I just
added up these two numbers to measure
the quality of each guess, which
actually worked better than you might
suspect. But it really didn't feel
systematic, and I'm sure there's other
approaches people could take, but here's
the one I landed on. If we're
considering the prospect of a next
guess, like in this case words, what we
really care about is the expected score
of our game if we do that. And to
calculate that expected score, we say
what's the probability that words is the
actual answer, which at the moment it
describes 58% to. We say with a 58%
chance, our score in this game would be
four.
And then with the probability of one
minus that 58%, um our score will be
more than that four.
How much more we don't know, but we can
estimate it based on how much
uncertainty there's likely to be once we
get to that point. Specifically, at the
moment there's 1.44 bits of uncertainty.
If we guess words, it's telling us the
expected information we'll get is 1.27
bits. So if we guess words, this
difference represents how much
uncertainty we're likely to be left with
after that happens. What we need is some
kind of function, which I'm calling F
here, that associates this uncertainty
with an expected score. And the way I
went about this was to just plot a bunch
of the data from previous games based on
version one of the bot to say, "Hey,
what was the actual score after various
points with certain very measurable
amounts of uncertainty?" For example,
these data points here that are sitting
above a value that's around like 8.7 or
so are saying for some games after a
point at which there were 8.7 bits of
uncertainty, it took two guesses to get
the final answer. For other games it
took three guesses. For other games it
took four guesses.
If we shift over to the left here, all
the points over zero are saying whenever
there's zero bits of uncertainty, which
is to say there's only one possibility,
then the number of guesses required is
always just one, which is reassuring.
Whenever there was one bit of
uncertainty, meaning it was essentially
just down to two possibilities, then
sometimes it required one more guess,
sometimes it required two more guesses,
and so on and so forth here.
Maybe a slightly easier way to visualize
this data is to bucket it together and
take averages.
For example, this bar here is saying
among all the points where we had one
bit of uncertainty, on average the
number of new guesses required was about
1.5.
And the bar over here is saying among
all of the different games where at some
point the uncertainty was a little above
four bits, which is like narrowing it
down to 16 different possibilities, then
on average it requires a little more
than two guesses from that point
forward. And from here I just did a
regression to fit a function that seemed
reasonable to this. And remember the
whole point of doing any of that is so
that we can quantify this intuition that
the more information we gain from a
word, the lower the expected score will
be.
So, with this as version 2.0, if we go
back and we run the same set of
simulations having it play against all
2,315
possible Wordle answers, how does it do?
Well, in contrast to our first version,
it's definitely better, which is
reassuring. All said and done, the
average is around 3.6. Although, unlike
the first version, there are a couple
times that it loses and requires more
than six in this circumstance,
presumably because there's times when
it's making that trade-off to actually
go for the goal rather than maximizing
information.
So, can we do better than 3.6?
We definitely can. Now, I said at the
start that it's most fun to try not
incorporating the true list of Wordle
answers into the way that it builds its
model. But, if we do incorporate it, the
best performance I could get was around
3.43.
So, if we try to get more sophisticated
than just using word frequency data to
choose this prior distribution, this
3.43 probably gives a max at how good we
could get with that, or at least how
good I could get with that. That best
performance essentially just uses the
ideas that I've been talking about here,
but it goes a little farther. Like it
does a search for the expected
information two steps forward rather
than just one. Originally I was planning
on talking more about that, but I
realize we've actually gone quite long
as it is. The one thing I'll say is
after doing this two-step search and
then running a couple sample simulations
in the top candidates, so far for me at
least it's looking like crane is the
best opener. Who would have guessed?
Also, if you use the true word list to
determine your space of possibilities,
then the uncertainty you start with is a
little over 11 bits. And it turns out
just from a brute force search, the
maximum possible expected information
after the first two guesses is around 10
bits.
Which suggests that best case scenario,
after your first two guesses with
perfectly optimal play, you'll be left
with around one bit of uncertainty.
Which is the same as being down to two
possible guesses. But I think it's fair
and probably pretty conservative to say
that you could never possibly write an
algorithm that gets this average as low
as three. Because with the words
available to you, there's simply not
room to get enough information after
only two steps to be able to guarantee
the answer in the third slot every
single time without fail.